Broadsides from Mexico Collection, 1676-1927, bulk 1820-1927
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Broadsides from Mexico Collection, 1676-1927, bulk 1820-1927
MS 339
This collection does not have any specific purchase or accession records in Special Collections which indicate its provenance. It was purchased in the 1970s from the Texas based Serendipity Co. The Lilly Library in Bloomington, Indiana sold these broadsides via Serendipity Co. because they were duplicates. There is a folder containing a control file documenting the provenance of a small number of related materials which have been incorporated into this collection
This collection contains approximately 2,000 Mexican broadsides, publicly distributed documents, issued by various offices of the federal, state, municipal, and local governments during the 19th and early 20th centuries. Apart from a few broadsides in French in the Zacatecas (5 of 5) folder, all the broadsides are in Spanish
8 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series:
Series I. State Broadsides, 1820-1927
Series II. Federal Government Broadsides, 1676-1910
Scope and Content Note
Topics referred to in these broadsides include invasions by Spain, France and the United States of America; mobilization for wars, including the Mexican American War; soldiers; elections; government positions; decretos (decrees); courts; prisoners; and financial issues, such as taxes, budgets, and customs. Often the broadsides in the individual state folders contain information from the federal government which the governor of the state released and signed. Some documents refer to the political conflicts between those who supported the Roman Catholic Church and those who advocated rigorous anti-clericalism. Also included are specific Plans, a 19th century aspect of Mexican political culture whereby a military or political leader would publish a Plan, usually named after where it was issued, and wait to see how many other political and military leaders would support it.
Santa Anna, Antonio López de, -- 1794?-1876; Bustamante, Anastasio, -- 1780-1853; Alamillo, J. Trinidad, -- 1857-1937; Juárez, Benito, -- 1806-1872; Gomez, Gilardo; Betancourt, Alberto; Iturbide, Agustín de, -- 1783-1824; Catholic Church -- Mexico -- History; Religion and politics -- Mexico; Church and state -- Mexico -- History; Printing -- Mexico; Politics and culture -- Mexico; Broadsides -- Mexico; Elections -- Mexico -- History; Mexican War, 1846-1848; Mexico -- Church history; Mexico -- History -- French Invasion, 1838-1839; Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1540-1810; Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1821-1861; Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1861-1867; Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1867-1910; Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1910-1946; Mexico -- History -- Spanish Invasion, 1829
Container List
- Series I: State Broadsides, 1820-1927
  - Aguascalientes, August 26, 1829 - October 19, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Subjects referred to are mobilization for wars, including the Mexican American War, soldiers, anti-clericalism, taxes, lists of jurors, and declarations of civil holidays at Christmas.
    Individuals mentioned include Felipe Cosio and Augustín Domingues.
    Two oversize items are located in Oversize Flat File.
  - Baja California, April 22, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chiapas, August 1, 1829 - June 10, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Subjects referred to are congressional fear of a Spanish invasion in 1829, government positions, the governor's speech opening a congressional session, and decretos (decrees) concerning securing property and financing for construction of a Palacio de los Supremos Poderes and a military parade ground.
    Individuals mentioned include Ignacio Barberena.
  - Chihuahua, March 6, 1829 - May 26, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Subjects referred to are congressional sessions, support of federal form of government for the nation, Roman Catholicism as the only state sanctioned religion, border disputes and alliances with Durango, judicial procedures, rebellion in various areas of Mexico including what is now New Mexico (1837), defeat of Texan invaders by soldiers from Santa Fe (1841), mobilization for wars, including the Mexican American War, soldiers, elections, taxes, government officials, and a 1910 contract signed by Porfirio Díaz deeding a small gold and silver mine to an American owned company. Plans mentioned include the Plan de Cuernavaca (1834) and the Plan de Jalapa (1850).
    Individuals mentioned include José Antonio Arce, José Isidro Madero, José S. Pareja, Albino Perez, José Gonzales, Manuel Armijo, José Mariano Monteverde, Ignacio Ocadiz, Estevan Aguirre, and Porfirio Díaz.
    One oversize item is located in Oversize Flat File.
  - Coahuila, October 17, 1829 - September 6, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Subjects referred to are decretos (decrees), state finances, government positions and appointments, taxes, budgets, elections, legislative pardons for prisoners, commutations of death sentences, a border conflict with Durango, cultivation of tobacco, and health and building codes. There are also permits to build electricity plants, telephone service, telegraph lines, and factories for producing various goods such as beer. There are no documents from the period of the Mexican American War.
    Individuals mentioned include Francisco Mejía, Miguel Cárdenas, Venustiano Carranza, Evaristo Madero, Hipólito Charles, Jesus de Valle, and Jesus Valdés Mejía.
  - Colima (1 of 3), July 10, 1829 - December 16, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Subjects referred to are decretos (decrees), contracts and announcements. Some topics referred to in these broadsides are government positions, state finances, taxes, budgets, elections, setting coach fares, land management, railroad construction, care of prisoners and syphilitic women, regulations against graffiti, monetary reform, tramway construction, thatch fences, regulations for pharmacies, weavers workshops, and slaughterhouses, education, and support of local students studying in other states. There is a fifty-nine year gap between the first document which refers to an anticipated Spanish invasion in 1829 and the rest of the broadsides which were issued in 1888 and 1889.
    Individuals mentioned include Gilardo Gómez and Alberto Betancourt and J. Trinidad Alamillo.
  - Colima (2 of 3), March 16, 1890 - December 16, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Subjects referred to are decretos (decrees), contracts, government positions, elections, taxes, state finances, monetary reform, pardons of prison sentences, imposition of the maximum sentence, education standards, support of local students studying in other states, standard weights and measures, business regulations, restriction of the hours during which bells could be rung in the capital, establishment of an orphanage, regulations regarding visible address tiles on residences, regulations against graffiti, regulation prohibiting people, horses and cattle from crossing railroad tracks, slaughterhouse regulations, contracts for electric lighting and tram construction, and permits to build factories for producing various goods such as ice.
    Individuals mentioned include Gilardo Gómez, Alberto Betancourt, and J. Trinidad Alamillo.
  - Colima (3 of 3), January 14, 1892 - August 8, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Subjects referred to are decretos (decrees), contracts, government positions, elections, taxes on coffee production, livestock and harvests, state finances, budgets, regulation prohibiting horsemen, carriages and cattle from crossing railroad tracks, registration of births, time limits for settling estates, definitions of injury, calumny, and defamation, fuel for public electric lighting, water shortages, pardon of the death penalty but commuted to maximum prison term, professional certification, education, widows and orphans, licenses for beggars, prohibitions against carrying arms, and regulations for slaughterhouses, coach fares, domestic servants, scribes and notaries.
    Individuals mentioned include J. Trinidad Alamillo, Gilardo Gómez, Alberto Betancourt, Miguel Alvarez, Remigio Rodríguez, and Francisco Santa Cruz.
  - Durango, August 27, 1828 - May 15, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Subjects referred to are government positions, criticisms and pleas from municipalities to the state government, state support for the Plan of Jalapa, state transfer of 30,000 pesos to the federal government, civilian militia, two senators appointed to manage state government when the state legislature was dissolved during a revolution in 1832, need for police in Durango when it became the state capital in 1844, and the new governor's letter to the citizens
    Individuals mentioned include Francisco Elorriaga, José Ignacio Gutierrez, and José A. Heredia.
    Eight oversize items are located in Oversize Flat File.
  - Guanajuato, December 22, 1828 - May 7, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Subjects referred to are government positions, expulsion of Spaniards from Mexico, the 1829 invasion by Spain, declaration of the end of the national emergency and a call for reestablishment of civil order, evacuation of Spaniards, coalition with Jalisco, Queretaro, Zacatecas, San Luis Potosi, Michoacan and Durango, blockade of Mexico by France, 1838 war with France, state request to the federal government asking punishment for those who support Mexico adopting a monarchical form of government, call for the end of the despotic administration of Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna, fund to aid those wounded defending the Constitution, list of citizens qualified to be elected to Congress, state payments to the federal government to help finance the war with Texas, declaration nullifying the 1846 elections, and economic measures during the Mexican American War.
    Individuals mentioned include Juan Morales, Antonio López de Santa Anna, and Lorenzo Arellano.
    Seven oversize items are located in Oversize Flat File.
  - Guerrero, March 16, 1910 - July 28, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Subjects referred to are decretos (decrees), reform of the penal code, fines assessed in courts, taxes, and the tax on the slaughter of cattle.
    Individuals mentioned include Silvano Saavedra, Damian Flores.
  - Jalisco, September 18, 1820 - August 19, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Subjects referred to are the Comandante General de Nueva Galicia freeing all French except criminals, independence, free establishment of factories, elimination of titles, certifications and union memberships as requirements for working at any profession, prohibiting cavalry escorts to all ranks below capitanes generales, the Roman Catholic Church, anticlericalism, civil versus clerical rights and monies, the Spanish Cortes, elections, support for the federal form of government, laws for Guadalajara, 1828 Spanish invasion, government positions, prisoners to work mines, Plan de Zavaleta, constitutional reform, ports for the Pacific trade, 1838 French invasion, tobacco monopoly, Plan de Cuernavaca, the Mexican American War, and monetary reform. Plans mentioned include the Plan de Cuernavaca.
    Individuals mentioned include José de la Cruz, Augustín Iturbide, Vicente Guerrero, José Ignacio Cañedo, Rafael Sanchez, Antonio López de Santa Anna and Joaquín Angulo.
    Fifty-five oversize items are located in Oversize Flat File
  - Mexico, April 5, 1823 - November 28, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Subjects referred to are recognizing Iturbide as emperor defined as treason, elections, courts, gauchupinesco, 1829 Spanish invasion, finances, budgets, taxes, government loans, customs, ports, government positions, army, support of the Catholic Church, anticlericalism, exile, asylum, honorific orders and decorations, support for widows of soldiers, 1838 French invasion, veterans, counterfeit money, Tacubaya, protecting Mexican industry from cheaper imports, factory seals to identify their products, amnesty for political prisoners, destruction of a building by soldiers and prisoners to build a plaza, caudillismo, Mexican American War, the coalition formed by the states of Aguascalientes, Jaliso, Michoacan, Querétaro, San Luis Potosí and Zacatecas, and recess of the state congress. Plans mentioned include the Plan de San Luis Potosí.
    Individuals mentioned include Augustín Iturbide, José Mariano Marin, Francisco Molinos del Campo, Lorenzo de Zavala, Anastasio Bustamante, José María Esquivel, José María Rozas, Mariano Buen Abad, Luis Gonzaga Vieyra, Antonio López de Santa Anna, Nicolás Bravo, Valentín Canalizo, Manuel Rincon, José Joaquín de Herrera, Mucio Barquera and Mariano Paredes y Arrillaga.
    Twenty-seven oversize items located in Oversize Flat File.
  - Michoacán, December 20, 1828 - July 3, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Morelos, January 5, 1910 - December 17, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Subjects referred to are government positions, public works department for the state, leave of absence for the governor, finances, taxes, alcohol, sugar, funding for medicine, meals and employees for seven state hospitals, schools, tax exemption for Roman Catholic Church justified by its good works and provision of free public education, taxation and regulation of the cattle industry, fees for rides in coaches, permission from federal government to import rifles and ammunition, and elections.
    Individuals mentioned include Pablo Escandon and Augustín Hurtado de Mendoza.
  - Nuevo León, January 28, 1828 - April 5, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Subjects referred to are government positions, lists of jurors, lists of voters, Roman Catholic Church, anticlericalism, state appropriation of Roman Catholic Church properties, public order restored by the garrison, submission of state governments to the federal government, support of Roman Catholic Church, military alliance with surrounding states, 1836 negotiations to release Santa Anna who was captured by Texans, 1838 break of diplomatic relations between France and Mexico, national foreign debt, revolution, support Plan de Jalisco, control Indian tribes on the frontier, Plan de San Luis Potosi, taxes, finances, Mexican American War, call to arms, draft all males between the ages of eighteen and fifty, and support of the federal government.
    Individuals mentioned include Manuel Mariano de Llano, José Rafael de la Garza, Gregorio Zambrano, Antonio López de Santa Anna, Juan Bautista de Arizpe, Juan Nepomuceno de la Garza y Evia, Mariano Paredes y Arrillaga, José María de Ortega, and Jesus Garza Gonzales.
  - Oaxaca, January 4, 1828 - April 28, 1838 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Subjects referred to are the opening statement of the Second Constitutional Congress expressing confidence in the rule of law after a period of turmoil, army, garrison, and the 1838 break of diplomatic relations between France and Mexico.
    Individuals mentioned include Francisco Monterrubio and José López de Ortigosa.
    One oversize items is located in Oversize Flat File.
  - Puebla, April 28, 1821 - December 25, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Subjects referred to are government positions, Plan de Iturbide, alliance with Oaxaca and Veracruz, end civil obligation to tithe, licenses for arms, army, garrison, elections, call to arms, 1838 French invasion, penalties for theft, roads, ports, cotton, Mexican American War, moving the seat of government, customs, state debt, cacao, taxes, judicial districts, anarchists, vagrants, restrict hours for ringing Church bells, Cinco de Mayo commemorations, education, mental hospital, state seals on documents, elections, squatters, war debt, fines, institution for deaf and dumb children, adult education, tax on imported flour, decretos (decrees), and abolition of road tolls.
    Individuals mentioned include Juan Mendoz, Augustín de Iturbide, Anastasio Bustamante, Juan Mugica y Osorio, Antonio López de Santa Anna, Patricio Fúrlong, Cosme Fúrlong, Rafael J. García, Cayetano María Perez de Leon, Manuel Rincon, Domingo Ybarra, Nicolás Bravo, Miguel C. de Alatriste, Benito Juárez and José de la Luz Palafox.
    Twenty-five oversize items are located in Oversize Flat File.
  - Querétaro, February 14, 1829 - June 30, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Subjects referred to are government positions, expulsion of Spaniards, revolt in Yucatan, Congress, military revolt in Jalapa, coalition with Durango, Guanajuato, Jalisco, Michoacan, San Luis Potosi, and Zacatecas, state funeral, courts, judges, support of federal government, Mexican American War, Battle of Cerro Gordo, protecting Mexican industry from cheaper imports, Roman Catholic Church, Mass, processions, 1838 French blockade, elections and state revenues.
    Individuals mentioned include José Rafael Canalizo, Lino Ramirez, and Miguel López de Ecala.
  - San Luis Potosí (1 of 2), November 25, 1826 - Nov. 28, 1848 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Subjects referred to are government positions, Spanish battle with Mexican forces under Santa Anna at Tampico in 1829, elections, Spanish conspirators, expulsion of Spaniards, support for the federal government, support for soldiers who fought the Spanish, salaries for government positions, robbery of a Roman Catholic Church, Plan de Jalapa, jurors, finances, taxes, alcabalas, excise taxes, state loans, judges, land sales by the government, soldiers, Mexican American War, ports, export duties, state funeral, tax relief for poor earning under 100 pesos per year, money, survey of prefecturas, arming rural ranches and haciendas, revolts in the mountains, tobacco, sentences for crimes, roads, Roman Catholic Church, wills, lumber imports, army, and the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo.
    Individuals mentioned include Julian de los Reyes, Antonio López de Santa Anna, Vicente Romero, Luis de Cortazar, Manuel Sanchez, José Maria Rincon Gallardo, José Maria Flores, Mariano Martinez, Matilde Ordáz, Juan José Zenon Fernandez, Manuel Gomez Pedrosa, Anastasio Bustamante, Juan Valentín Amador, Ramon Adame, and José María Otahegui.
    Ten oversize items are located in Oversize Flat File.
  - San Luis Potosí (2 of 2), April 24, 1850 - Nov. 29, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Subjects referred to are government positions, elections, state appointment of bishops, soldiers, army, constitutional reform, Masses said for Iturbide and the army, congressional agenda, Baja California, support for the horses of army personnel, health of army personnel, Indian tribes, judges, courts, legislators, senate, governor, anarchy, finances, budgets, taxes, loans, state and federal debts, levy of mounted men to maintain safety on the roads, amnesty for revolutionaries, tierras baldias colonizable by corporations, counterfeit money, professional certification, customs, ports, defense of the Isthmus of Tehuantepec, Mexican American War, local wines and aguardientes, defense of Matamoros, monopoly for playing cards, salaries, public granary, grain, ranches and haciendas, civil unrest, La Reforma, alliance with Zacatecas, Aguascalientes, Guanajuato, Morelia, and Tamaulipas, compensation for property ruined during the war for La Reforma, martial law, honorific titles, levies, exile of reactionary soldiers, federal constitution, pardon for all sentenced to corporal punishment except murderers, revolutionaries, and a proclamation denying state recognition of foreign authorities.
    Individuals mentioned include Julian de los Reyes, José Joaquín Herrera, Miguel Laso, José Guadalupe de los Reyes, Mariano Arista, Manuel Díaz de la Vega, Vicente Chico Sein, Benito Juárez, Francisco P. Villanueva and Sóstenes Escandon.
  - Sinaloa, October 31, 1833 - November 29, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Subjects referred to are government positions, the Mexican American War, call to arms, and call for unity.
    Individuals mentioned include Carlos Espinosa de los Monteros.
    Three oversize items are located in Oversize Flat File.
  - Sonora, February 25, 1832 - May 21, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Subjects referred to are ports, state congress' rejection of federal congress' proposed constitutional reforms which limited states rights, and the Mexican American War.
    Individuals mentioned include Antonio López de Santa Anna, José Ramon Terrazas, Manuel Escalante y Mason, and Juan Bautista Gandara.
  - Tamaulipas, November 20, 1829 - June 30, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Subjects referred to are 1828 Spanish invasion, support of the federal system of government, state legislature's dismissal of the governor, elections, and municipal government regulations.
    Individuals mentioned include José Antonio Fernandez and Gregorio de Leon.
  - Tlaxcala, September 21, 1828 - 1829 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Subjects referred to are the 1829 Spanish invasion and soldiers.
    Individuals mentioned include José Antonio de Saldaña and Cristóbal Gonzalez Angulo.
  - Veracruz, May 30, 1820 - February 1, 1834 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Subjects referred to are elections, aid for the widows of those killed during the 1828 Spanish invasion, and congress.
    Individuals mentioned include José Davila Davila, Antonio Juille y Moreno, Antonio López de Santa Anna and Leonardo Romay.
  - Yucatán, January 4, 1834 - January 2, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Subjects referred to are the state army, jurors, and Yucatán's refusal to recognize the federal government because it broke the pact which tied Yucátan to the rest of the republic.
    Individuals mentioned include Francisco Martinez de Arredondo, José Tiburcio López, and Miguel Barbachano.
  - Zacatecas (1 of 5), July 1, 1824 - December 14, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Subjects referred to are constitutions, laws, decretos (decrees), government positions, finances, taxes, tobacco, alcohol, legitimacy, Roman Catholic Church, clergy, cattle, civil militia, loans from the state to the federal government, draft, juntas patrioticas, army, soldiers, judges, certification of doctors, Spanish colonial rule, independence, elections, anticlericalism, suspension of the federal government's religious reforms which were rejected by most of the nation to maintain peace, threatened invasion by Durango, 1836 war with Texas, pardons for Texan prisoners, changes in the departamento status of Texas, New Mexico, California, Coahuila, Colima, and Tlaxcala, French blockade, customs, ports, aid from the state to pueblos during epidemics, mints, copper, contraband, and Tacubaya.
    Individuals mentioned include Pedro José Lopez de Nava, Francisco Garcia, Vicente Guerro, Mariano del Castillo, José A. Heredia, Manuel G. Cosio, Santiago Villegas, Fernando Franco, and Antonio López de Santa Anna.
    One hundred forty-three oversize items are located in Oversize Flat File.
  - Zacatecas (2 of 5), January 3, 1851 - December 10, 1853 (Box 4, Folder 1)